Inventory of the Justin Liuba papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Justin Liuba papers
1953-2010
2011C17
Hoover Institution Archives
1 manuscript box and 2 oversize boxes (3.1 linear feet)
Correspondence, writings, memoranda, printed matter, and sound recording cassettes, relating to Radio Free Europe broadcasts to Romania, and to political conditions in Romania, Romanian history, and Romanian émigré affairs. Includes interviews conducted by Justin Liuba for Radio Free Europe broadcasts.
Liuba, Justin.
Access
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2011.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Liuba, a journalist in the United States and Europe, was an editor, writer, and analyst for Radio Free Europe. He served under Commissioner McCloy in the Special Program for Denazification of German Youth and as an official for the Iuliu Maniu American Romanian Relief Foundation.
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, writings, memoranda, printed matter, and sound recording cassettes, relating to Radio Free Europe broadcasts to Romania, and to political conditions in Romania, Romanian history, and Romanian émigré affairs. Includes interviews conducted by Justin Liuba for Radio Free Europe broadcasts.
Iuliu Maniu American Romanian Relief Foundation.; Radio Free Europe.; Phonotapes.; Radio broadcasting--Romania.; Romania--History.; Romania--Politics and government.; Romanians--United States.
- Sound and video recordings, 1986-2009. (Box 1-2)
  Scope and Contents note
  Compact sound cassettes and VHS video tapes describing political conditions in Romania, Romanian history, and Romanian émigré affairs for Radio Free Europe broadcasts to Romania and the Iuliu Maniu Foundation. Includes interviews conducted by Justin Liuba for Radio Free Europe broadcasts. Titles derived from Justin Lubia's list or tape label, some titles do not have a date specified.
  - Sound recordings on compact sound cassette, 1986-2009 (Tape 1-2:)
    - RFE (Radio Free Europe) Justin Liuba (nom de plume Dan Valceanu) interviews Dr. Petre Vlad, eyewitness to 1918 Assembly in Alba Iulia (Tape 1: 1)
    - RFE report on Moldova's admission to the UN, 1992 (Tape 1: 2)
    - RFE interview with Ion Caramitru, artist visiting USA 1995 (Tape 1: 3)
    - RFE report on Princess Marie of Romania's wedding, New York, 1995 (Tape 1: 4)
    - RFE Review of film NADJA with Elina Lowenson, of Romanian background (Tape 1: 5)
    - RFE interview with Elina Lowenson, actress, 1995 (Tape 1: 6)
    - RFE report by Dr. Anton Crihan, eyewitness of Assembly in Chishinau proclaiming unification with Romania in 1918 (Tape 1: 7)
    - RFE interview with Dr. Anton Crihan regarding Bessarabia's unification with Romania in 1918 (Tape 1: 8)
    - RFE interview with Reverend Laslo Tokes, Hungarian leader in Romania, 1990 (Tape 1: 9)
    - RFE Salute to Moldavians/Bessarbians, by Dr. Anton Crihan, 1990 (Tape 1: 10)
    - Interview (published, but not broadcast) with futurologist Elizabeth Florescu, Boston, 2010 (Tape 1: 11)
    - Bessarabia's Unification festivity at the Iuliu Maniu Foundation, New York, 2003. Speakers include Justin Liuba and Nicholas Dima (Tape 1: 12)
    - RFE interview with Radu Campeanu, a political leader in New York (Tape 1: 13)
    - RFE report on King Michael's luncheon at the Forbes Foundation in New York, 1991 (Tape 1: 14)
    - RFE report on King Michael's arrival in New York, 1991 (Tape 1: 15)
    - RFE Munich Headquarters interview of King Michael by E. Hurezeanu, Geneva, 1989 (Tape 1: 16)
    - Festivity at the Iuliu Maniu Foundation on the Unification of Romanian Principalities in 1959, 1990. Speaker: Justin Liuba (Tape 1: 17)
    - RFE report on Romanian anti-communist demonstration in New York, November 26, 1989 (Tape 1: 18)
    - Raw sound material from a Romanian demonstration, New York, December 21, 1989 (Tape 1: 19)
    - Festivity at the Iuliu Maniu Foundation in New York, 1990. Singer: Antonela Stoica, speaker: Justin Liuba (Tape 1: 20)
    - Voice of America (VOA) interview by Nicholas Dima with Justin Liuba, New York, 2000 (Tape 1: 21)
    - Festivity at the Iuliu Maniu Foundation, New York, 1996. Speaker: Justin Liuba on "Leaders of the World" (Tape 1: 22)
    - Raw material, speech by Emil Constantinescu, political leader at the Waldorf Astoria, New York, 1996 (Tape 1: 23)
    - Open letter by Reverend Simion Mesaros of Baia Mare, Romania, to the Director of Radio Free Europe (Tape 1: 24)
    - Festivity at the Iuliu Maniu Foundation, 1988. Speaker: Princess Ileana of Romania (Mother Alexandra) (Tape 1: 25)
    - RFE interview with Dr. Stefan Issarescu, leader of the Resistance, 2006 (Tape 1: 26)
    - RFE interview with Valery Oisteanu, writer, 1995 (Tape 1: 27)
    - Festivity at the Iuliu Maniu Foundation, 1987. Speaker: Ariane Popa on the Unification of Romanian Principalities of Jan. 24, 1989 (Tape 1: 28)
    - A Radio Free Europe broadcast to Romania from Munich on Dec 24, 1989 (Tape 1: 29)
    - Festivity at the Iuliu Maniu Foundation, New York, 1998. Speaker: Ariane Popa on Romanian treasure in Russia and Nicholas Dima on the present situation in Bessarabia (Tape 1: 30)
    - RFE interview with Dr. Ing. Simiu (DC) on Queen Elena's saving Jews (Tape 1: 31)
    - RFE interview with Gregor von Rezzori, writer of Romanian background (Tape 1: 32)
    - Festivity at the Iuliu Maniu Foundation. Speaker: US Ambassador to Romania, David Funderburk (Tape 1: 33)
    - Festivity at the Iuliu Maniu Foundation, Bessarabia and Bukovina Anniversary. Speakers: Ariane Popa, Dinu Giurescu (Tape 1: 34)
    - Festivity at the Iuliu Maniu Foundation, Bessarabia and Bukovina Anniversary. Speaker: Professor Charles King, Georgetown University (Tape 1: 35)
    - Raw sound material: Romanian anti-communist demonstration in New York 1989 (Tape 1: 36)
    - Interview with a veteran (Korean War) hospitalized in New York (Andrei Porumbeanu); name changed to Prombescu (Tape 1: 37)
    - Festivity at the Iuliu Maniu Foundation, Bessarabia and Bucovina Anniversary. Speaker: Professor Charles King, Georgetown University, 2000 (Tape 2: 38)
    - Festivity at the Iuliu Maniu Foundation. Speaker: Cornel Nistorescu, Romanian journalist, 2005 (Tape 2: 39)
    - Festivity at the Iuliu Maniu Foundation, Bessarabia and Bucovina Anniversary. Speaker: Daniel Ross, State Department, 2001 (Tape 2: 40)
    - Interview by Liviu Floda (RFE) with I.R. Somuz, former member of the Socialist Party/Romania about Ch. Dej and N. Ceausescu (Tape 2: 41)
    - RFE interview with Carolina Herrera, fashion designer, New York (Tape 2: 42)
    - RFE interview with George Soros, philanthropist (Tape 2: 43)
    - RFE interview with C.Z. Guest, dean of New York society, author, 1986 (Tape 2: 44)
    - RFE interview with Peggy Noonan, speech writer to President Ronald Reagan (Tape 2: 45)
    - RFE interview with Jacqueline Susan, author The Love Machine (Tape 2: 46)
    - RFE interview with Dr. Jurgen Trumpf, Secretary General of Council of the European Union (Tape 2: 47)
    - RFE interview with John Whitehead, Deputy Secretary of State, on Ceausescu (Tape 2: 48)
    - RFE interview with Averell Harriman, diplomat, on Romania's contribution (Tape 2: 49)
    - RFE interview with Anna Moffo, soprano, about State dinner honoring President Ceausescu of Romania (Tape 2: 50)
    - RFE interview with Georgette Mossbacher, cosmetic queen, fundraiser (Tape 2: 51)
    - RFE interview with Hugh Downs, TV personality on NBC, after the Romanian visit (Tape 2: 52)
    - RFE interview with Bob Guccione, publishing tycoon Penthouse Magazine (Tape 2: 53)
    - RFE interview with Marion Javits, wife of U.S. Senator (R) New York J. Javits (Tape 2: 54)
    - RFE interview with Hannah Pakula, author, after visit to Romania (Tape 2: 55)
    - Interview with explorer Dr. Robert Rines, about Loch Ness monster, 2009. Not broadcast (Tape 2: 56)
    - Festivity at the Iuliu Maniu Foundation, Bessarabia and Bucovina Anniversary, 2000. Speaker: J. Rickert, U.S. State Department (Tape 2: 57)
    - Festivity at the Iuliu Maniu Foundation, 1999. Speaker: US Ambassador to Romania, J. Rosapepe (Tape 2: 58)
    - Interview with Bill Bueche, UFO researcher, Boston. NOT Broadcast (Tape 2: 59)
    - Speech by Justin Liuba at Columbia University meeting organized by Greek magazine Krikos on Greek-Romanian relations, 1990. Not broadcast (Tape 2: 60)
    - American anthem, Romanian anthem (Traiasca Regele) (Tape 2: Unnumbered)
  - Video recordings on VHS tapes, undated (Tape 2)
    - "The Inner Prison," documentary by C. Jacobson (Tape 2)
    - Romanian royal visit to New York airport and the Waldorf Astoria (Tape 2)
    - Romanian royal visit to New York, meeting at offices of Radio Free Europe with Princess Margarita (Tape 2)
- Papers, 1953-2010. (Box 3)
  Contains articles and correspondence relating to Radio Free Europe and de-Nazification. Includes Liuba's published articles on both subjects.
  - Articles published by or mentioning Liuba, relating to Radio Free Europe and denazification, 1953-1993 (Folder 3)
  - Correspondence relating to Liuba's work at Radio Free Europe, 1958-1993. (Folder 3)
    In Romanian and English
  - Photograph of Romanian anti-Communist resistance members, 2010. (Folder 3)
    Includes Liuba